Thomas T. Craven Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Thomas T. Craven Papers 1842-1969 1917-1945
MSS61733
Craven, Thomas T. (Thomas Tingey), 1873-1950
500 items
2 containers plus 1 oversize
.6 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, family papers, and subject files relating primarily to his convoy duty and command of United States Naval Aviation Forces in Europe during World War I, and his command of a gunboat flotilla on the Yangtze River in China during 1929-1931.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Byrd, Richard Evelyn, 1888-1957--Correspondence.; Cone, Hutchinson Ingham, 1871-1941--Correspondence.; Cooke, Morris Llewellyn, 1872-1960--Correspondence.; Craven, Thomas T. (Thomas Tingey), 1873-1950.; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948--Correspondence.; Earle, Ralph, 1874-1939--Correspondence.; Hooper, Stanford Caldwell, 1884-1955--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Kimmel, Husband Edward, 1882-1968.; Knox, Dudley Wright, 1877-1960--Correspondence.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944--Correspondence.; Sarnoff, David, 1891-1971--Correspondence.; Sims, William Sowden, 1858-1936--Correspondence.; Watson, Edward H. (Edward Howe), 1873-1942.
Organizations
New York State Maritime Academy.; United States Naval Academy--Curricula.; United States. Bureau of the Budget. Federal Coordinating Service.; United States. Navy--Foreign service--China--Yangtze River.; United States. Navy. Destroyer Squadron 11.; United States. Navy. Naval Aviation Forces.; United States. Navy. Pacific Fleet.
Subjects
Aircraft carriers.; Budget--United States.; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry.; Fisheries--Alaska.; Gunboats.; Merchant marine--United States.; Naval convoys--Atlantic Ocean.; Naval convoys--Mediterranean Sea.; Navy-yards and naval stations, American--Corrupt practices.; Pearl Harbor (Hawaii), Attack on, 1941.; Radio--Law and legislation--United States.; Shipwrecks--California--Honda, Point.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of Thomas T. Craven were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1984 and converted to a gift in 1998.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Thomas T. Craven are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1873, July 8 Born, Vallejo, Calif.
1896 Graduated, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1901 Married Antoinette Merritt
1908 Served as gunnery officer, South Carolina (battleship)
1915 Attended Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1916 1918 Commanded Sacramento (gunboat)
1918 Commanded United States Naval Aviation Forces in Europe
1919 1921 Director of naval aviation; ordered conversion of the Jupiter (collier) into the Langley (aircraft carrier)
1922 Commanded Destroyer Squadron Fifteen in early charting of Atlantic Ocean floor using sound equipment
1923 Defended Edward H. Watson in court-martial resulting from mass shipwreck at Point Honda, Calif.
1927 1928 Director of naval communications
1928 Promoted to rear admiral; commanded Great Lakes Naval Training Station, Great Lakes, Ill.
1929 1931 Commander, Yangtze Patrol, China
1931 1933 Chief coordinator, Federal Coordinating Service, Bureau of the Budget
1935 Commander, Battleship Division One
1937 Commandant, Thirteenth Naval District, Bremerton, Wash.
1937 Retired from active naval service
1942 1946 Recalled to active duty; superintendent, New York State Maritime Academy, Fort Schuyler, N.Y.
1950, Apr. 5 Died, St. Albans, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Thomas Tingey Craven (1873-1950), naval officer, span the years 1842-1969, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period 1917-1945. Craven is noted as the director of naval aviation who ordered the conversion of the coal-carrying ship Jupiter into the Langley, the United States Navy's first aircraft carrier. The collection is organized into family papers, general correspondence, subject files, and writings. The family papers include biographical and genealogical material, clippings, and correspondence. Of special interest are a letter of 1842 written by Craven's grandfather and namesake Thomas T. Craven, and a letter from Craven to his wife Antoinette relating his experiences and impressions during the 1908 visit of the battleship South Carolina to Japan.
Well represented in the Subject File are documents related to Craven's World War I convoy duty in Atlantic and Mediterranean waters while captain of the gunboat Sacramento from 1917 to 1918, his command of the United States Naval Aviation Forces in Europe in 1918, and his command of a gunboat flotilla on the Yangtze River in China from 1929 to 1931. Documents relating to Craven's World War I service include convoy sailing orders, reports about naval accidents and incidents, and correspondence and memoranda relating to United States Naval Aviation Forces in Europe. Correspondents from the latter period include Hutchinson I. Cone and Ralph Earle. As commander of the Yangtze Patrol (1929-1931), Craven corresponded with diplomats, missionaries, military colleagues, and Chinese officials. Correspondents from this period include Morris Llewellyn Cooke, H. G. C. Hallock, Lieu Ven Tae (or Liu Wen-tau), M. Yonai, Marshal Liu Hsiang, and Allen N. Cameron. Other topics include Craven's service as defense counsel in the court-martial of Edward H. Watson, commander of a destroyer squadron that shipwrecked at Point Pedernales (or Point Honda) on the California coast in 1923, resulting in the loss of twenty-three men and seven ships; and Craven's efforts in behalf of a protégé, Husband E. Kimmel, who was under investigation after the 1942 Japanese attack on his Pacific Fleet command at Pearl Harbor.
The General Correspondence includes letters discussing Craven's service as chief coordinator of the Federal Coordinating Service during the Herbert Hoover administration, curriculum reform at the United States Naval Academy, the New York State Maritime Academy, the Merchant Marine, Alaska fisheries, aircraft carriers, radio communications policy, corrupt practices in naval shipyards, and other topics. Correspondents not already cited include Richard E. Byrd, Josephus Daniels, Stanford C. Hooper, Herbert Hoover, Dudley W. Knox, Frank Knox, David Sarnoff, and William S. Sims.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Family papers (Box 1)
  - Biographical material, 1921-1943, undated (Box 1)
  - Craven, Antoinette (wife), 1924-1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Family history material, 1920-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Letters (Box 1)
    - 1842, 1872, with cover letter, 1944 (Box 1)
    - 1908-1931, undated (Box 1)
- General correspondence (Box 1)
  - "B-G" miscellaneous, 1914-1945 (Box 1)
  - Hooper, Stanford C., 1922-1937 (Box 1)
  - Hoover, Herbert, 1927-1943 (Box 1)
  - "H-J" miscellaneous, 1908-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - Kimmel, Husband E., 1936 (Box 1)
  - Knox, Dudley W., 1931-1945 (Box 1)
  - "K-P" miscelllaneous, 1907-1945, undated (Box 1)
  - "R-Y" miscellaneous, 1920-1945, undated (Box 1)
- Subject file (Box 1)
  - Aircraft carriers, 1943 (Box 1)
  - Awards, medals, and honors, 1919-1921 (Box 1)
  - Convoy duty, sailing orders, and related material, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Nahma (armed yacht) incident, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Naval cruises, souvenir books, and rosters, 1908-1925 (Box 1)
  - Olympia (cruiser) grounding, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Passport, 1918 (Box 1)
  - Pearl Harbor attack investigation, 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - Point Honda (Calif.) naval disaster, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Puget Sound Navy Yard, Bremerton, Wash., 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  - Retirements, 1937, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - United States Naval Aviation Forces in Europe (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 1)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 2)
  - Whiting, Kenneth, 1943 (Box 2)
  - Yangtze Patrol, 1929-1931 See also Oversize (Box 2)
- Writings, 1919-1953, undated (Box 2)
- Subject file (Box OV 1)
  - Yangtze Patrol, 1929 (Container 2) (Box OV 1)